Guide to the Cornwall Legal Miscellanea 1757-1941 MS 017 MS 017 MS 017
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Legal Miscellanea
1757-1941
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 017
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
This collection consists of legal matters relating to the town of Cornwall.
Provenance
unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Several individuals in this collection were from the community. John Quincy Adams (1837-1913) was a native of Cornwall who was admitted to the county bar in 1865. Adams was active in the affairs of the Second Congregational Church and a well-respected attorney. He removed to Michigan in 1872. Robert B. Newett (1858-1916) was born in West Cornwall and served as the chief of the Torrington Police Department. Leonard James Nickerson (1857-1937) was also born in Cornwall and educated in the community’s public schools, as well as the Alger Institute. Nickerson represented Cornwall in the Connecticut assembly in 1883, and was appointed a judge in 1923. Martin B. Thomas served as an attorney in Cornwall during the early nineteenth century, although little information is known of his background.
The majority of legal professionals in this collection moved to Cornwall from elsewhere. Edwin Baldwin (unknown-unknown) was a summer resident and attorney from New York. William Daniel Bosler (1877-1944) was originally from New York, but moved to Cornwall to study under L.J. Nickerson sometime prior to 1902. After several years in Cornwall, Bosler returned to New York City, where he worked for Tammany Hall. Arthur D. Warner (1848-1915) was another legal professional who moved to Cornwall. In 1872, he opened a legal practice in West Cornwall, where he remained for eleven years before returning to his hometown of Woodbury, Connecticut. Josepha Newcomb Whitney (1871-after 1946) was a summer resident who was active in the fight for women’s suffrage. Her husband was Edward B. Whitney, Esq. Judge James P. Woodruff (1868-1931) was originally from Litchfield, but studied at the Housatonic Valley Institute in Cornwall.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is primarily comprised of miscellaneous legal documents, such as indentures, contracts, and court cases, as well as items relating to individuals with Cornwall ties who worked in the legal profession. The first section contains legal documents organized in chronological order, the second section is devoted to legal professionals organized in alphabetical order, and the third section contains miscellaneous items.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Legal Documents
Legal Professionals
Miscellaneous
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Suffragettes--Unites States.; Woman Suffrage--Connecticut.; Woman Suffrage--United States.; Woman's rights--Unites States.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Articles; legal documents; Cornwall Historical Society; Cornwall Historical Society; Adams, John Quincy (1837-1913); Newett, Robert B. (1858-1916); Nickerson, Leonard James (1857-1937); Bosler, William Daniel (1877-1944); Baldwin, Edwin; Warner, Arthur D. (1848-1915); Whitney, Josepha Newcomb (1871-1946); Woodruff, James P. (1868-1931)
- Legal Documents
  - Indenture of George Cornelius, Indian, to be the servant of David Rose, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Complaint against Cornwall deputy Woodruff Emons, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Selectmen’s appointment of John Clothier as Thomas Harris’ legal guardian, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Complaint by town of Cornwall against town of Goshen, for poor road conditions, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Complaint against Henry Tibbals, et al. for Sabbath-breaking, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Property agreement between Ebenezer Birdseye and Benjamin Bell, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bond of Truman Baldwin and Nathan Lamson, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Complaint against Calvin Butler, for Sabbath-breaking, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Binding agreement between George Chambers and Joseph Buckley, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Court order for payment of Dwight W. Pierce, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter attesting to kleptomania of Mrs. Beebe, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Arrest warrant for Hercules Sharp, for debt, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Charles Hiltmeyer v. James F. Reed, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Summons for L.H. Carroll, et al., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - State of Connecticut v. George Potter, for illegal saloon-keeping, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - State of Connecticut v. Ed Smith, for assault of Thomas Dougherty, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - George E. Bierce v. The Sharon Electric Light Co., for trespassing, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Julia C. Breen v. Town of Cornwall, for poor road conditions, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Andrew M. Clark v. Town of Cornwall, et al., for poor road conditions, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Property appraisal of Grace Liner Drobish by Sheriff Frank H. Turkington, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “The Smith Brothers Case,” about murders of George and David Smith, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Legal Professionals
  - John Quincy Adams correspondence, 1896-1917 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - John Quincy Adams portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Edwin Baldwin letter regarding road conditions, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - William D. Bosler journal articles, 1899-1921 (Box 1, Folder 29-34)
  - William D. Bosler letter to E.C. Starr, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Obituary for police chief Robert B. Newett, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Newspaper articles regarding Leonard Jones Nickerson, 1895-1923; , undated (Box 1, Folder 37-51)
  - Leonard Jones Nickerson correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1897-1923 (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
  - Obituaries of Leonard Jones Nickerson, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letter written by William Lewis about Cornwall attorney Martin B. Thomas, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Arthur D. Warner, Esq. correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Newspaper article about Arthur D. Warner appropriating funds, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Letter sent by Mrs. E.B. Whitney, the former Josepha Newcomb, to E.C. Starr, about suffrage movement, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - James P. Woodruff correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Newspaper articles regarding James P. Woodruff, 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newspaper clippings about Connecticut Blue Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 64-65)
  - Emancipation petition for enslaved Cornwall woman, Pegg, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 66)